Guide to the E. Tappan Stannard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
E. Tappan Stannard papers
1909-1949
MS 890
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The papers consist of correspondence, photographs, and memorabilia. The correspondence (1939-1949) is entirely devoted to Stannard's participation in the development of the sciences at Yale University and as a member of various university committees. A photograph album depicting the construction of the Copper River and Northwestern Railway in Alaska (ca. 1909-1910) is also included.
Stannard, Earl Tappan, 1882-1949
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the E. Tappan Stannard estate.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Earl Tappan Stannard Papers consist primarily of correspondence concerned with the development of the sciences at Yale University. Stannard was a frequent member of university fact-finding committees. Among them were the President's Committee for the Sciences, the University Council, Division of the Sciences, and the President's Committee on University Development, division of engineering of which he was chairman.
Of particular interest in the papers is a photograph album depicting the construction of the Copper River and Northwestern Railway, Copper River, Alaska (ca. 1909-1910). The papers came to Manuscripts and Archives from William J. Feeney, Associate Treasurer of Yale University on March 20, 1979. The Treasurer's office received the material from the E. Tappan Stannard Estate.
Biographical / Historical
E. Tappan Stannard, '05 S.
Stannard was born December 9, 1882, in Chittenango, New York, the son of Burdette and Valenta (Young) Stannard. He prepared for Yale at Phillips Academy, Andover, was graduated from the Sheffield Scientific School with the degree of Bachelor of Philosophy in 1905, and spent the following year there in graduate work.
In June, 1906, he entered the employ of the Federal Lead Company in Missouri, where he remained nearly five years. Then followed three years with the Braden Copper Company in Chile and five years in Alaska as General Manager of the mining operations of the Kennecott Copper Corporation. In 1920 he became head also of the Alaska Steamship Company. In 1923 he was elected vice president and a director of the Kennecott Copper Corporation and since 1933 has been its president. He was president also of the Braden Copper Company and an officer or director of several other companies, including the Chase Brass and Copper Company and Johns-Manville Corporation.
He headed the United States Copper Association and was instrumental in working out a cooperative understanding with world producers of copper, in recognition of which he was decorated by King Leopold of Belgium. In 1936 the Michigan College of Mines and Technology conferred upon him the honorary degree of Doctor of Engineering.
Stannard was vice-president of his Class, a member of the Executive Committee of the Yale Engineering Association, and was a Republican and an Episcopalian.
He married Jeannette Condon on June 11, 1918.
[from the Yale University Alumni Board ballot, May 1, 1939]
Engineering; Railroads -- Alaska; Science; Alaska; West (U.S.); Stannard, Earl Tappan, 1882-1949; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale Corporation; Yale University. School of Engineering
- Inventory
  - Alumni convocation, "Engineering at Yale," speech given by E. T. Stannard, 1941 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical statement from Alumni Board ballot, 1939 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, committee on honorary degrees, Yale University, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence re: President's Committee for the Sciences, Yale University, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence re: reorganization of Sheffield Scientific School, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re: President's Committee on University Development, Division of Engineering, 1939-1940 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence re: President's Committee on University Development, Division of Engineering, 1940 June-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence re: Stone Trust Corporation Endowment Fund, Yale University, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence re: University Council, Committee on the Division of Sciences, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence re: Yale Engineering Association, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence re: Silliman College, Yale Graduate Placement Committee, Alumni Board; and miscellaneous letters, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reports, President's Committee on University Development, Division of Engineering, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - E. T. Stannard's appointment to the Belgian League of Honor, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Introducing Tough Guy, book by Robert H. Ramaga, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Oil painting, "Alaska Summit," by "Jules", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Notebook of Jeannette Condon Stannard, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of E. T. Stannard, [Jeannette Condon Stannard?], and unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of the Copper River and Northwestern Railway, Copper River, Alaska, 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 18)